Guide to the Samuel Herbert Fisher Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Herbert Fisher papers
1916-1954
MS 213
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
(26 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence and background material which document Samuel Fisher's service to Yale University and his research on the eighteenth century Litchfield, Connecticut printer Thomas Collier. The papers detail Fisher's involvement as a member of the Yale graduate committee on university development and his plan for reorganization of the university (1919). The papers also highlight Fisher's role in Yale's search for a new president (1920-1921) and his influence in the development of the residential college system.
Fisher, Samuel H. (Samuel Herbert), 1867-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Robert L. Fisher and Mrs. Theodore Babbitt, 1961, and George W. Pierson, n.d.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Yale University Files, 1916-1954. II. Thomas Collier Files, 1930-1948.
Scope and Contents
The Samuel Herbert Fisher Papers consist of correspondence and background material which document Samuel Fisher's service to Yale University and his historical research and writing. Though the papers detail Fisher's involvement as a member of the Yale graduate committee on university development and his plan for the reorganization of the university (1919), the bulk of the papers focus on Fisher's role as a member of the Yale University Corporation (1920-1935). The papers record the corporation decisions during this period which significantly changed Yale's administration, physical plant, student housing, and course of study. They highlight Yale's search for a new president (1920-1921), James Rowland Angell's presidency, the major building programs made possible by the gifts of John Sterling and Edward S. Harkness, and the development of the residential college system. The papers do not include any of Fisher's legal files, and thus his role as junior counsel to Yale University and as personal counsel to Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness and Edward S. Harkness is not documented. Historical research files testify to Fisher's interests in the history of Litchfield, Connecticut
Robert L. Fisher and Mrs. Theodore Babbitt donated a portion of their father's papers to the Yale University Library in 1961. George W. Pierson received several files of papers from Samuel Fisher in the 1940s while working on his history of Yale. (See folder 116). These files subsequently became part of the Fisher Papers in the Manuscripts and Archives Department. The papers are arranged in two series.
Series I is the larger of the two and comprises seventy-five percent of the papers.
Series I consists of topical files which are arranged in alphabetical order. Almost all files include correspondence but may also contain related minutes, reports, charts, and printed material. There are files for all the committees on which Fisher served and for many administrative offices and Yale organizations. There are also voluminous files concerning the Yale class of 1889, its donations to the university, and its reunions. Correspondence with a particular individual may be in several different files.
University reorganization is the subject of the files for the Alumni Committee of Yale University (folders 3-24). Correspondence between Fisher and fellow committee members and also with University Secretary Anson Phelps Stokes concerns the existing division of functions between Yale College and Sheffield Scientific School. The committee's report, issued in February, 1919, proposed changes in the structure of the university, a common freshman year and the addition to the administration of a provost and a dean of students. Correspondence following the appearance of the report contains reactions from alumni, faculty, and university officers such as Charles Seymour and Lewis S. Welch. Correspondence in the fall of 1919 also includes discussions of candidates to fill the new administrative positions.
Building Committee files (folders 26-45) concern Fisher's interests in changes to the physical plant of the university from 1920 to 1922 and from 1933 to 1935. The files include general discussions of architectural plans for the university's development as well as correspondence with architects, contractors, and suppliers concerning specific buildings such as Sterling Chemistry Laboratory and Sterling Hall of Medicine. Folders 144-145 concern buildings for the School of Forestry.
In the files under the heading "Corporation" is correspondence with individual corporation members and administrative officers as well as with alumni concerned with matters under the corporation's consideration. Many letters relate to the selection of new corporation members. Also in these files are discussions of student drunkenness, a presidential residence, academic appointments, improvements in graduate education, and undergraduate housing needs. The correspondence with Lewis Welch in these files is particularly substantive. Additional files relating to Yale's plan for residential colleges are found under the subjects "Educational Policy" and "Yale University: general." Similar discussions are found in the files for "President," "Provost," "Secretary," and "Treasurer."
The papers include two boxes of material relating to the work of a committee to receive suggestions of candidates for the Yale presidency, which Fisher chaired beginning in April, 1920. Incoming letters containing suggestions are voluminous, and many letters also contain reflections on the Hadley presidency and the qualities sought in the new president. The most frequent names mentioned are Anson Phelps Stokes, Charles Seymour, and Henry Sloane Coffin. The files also include Fisher's correspondence with fellow committeemen such as John V. Farwell and reports and lists submitted to the corporation.
The files for the Yale Alumni University Fund Association and the Yale College Class of 1889 are also voluminous, and both document Fisher's efforts as a fund-raiser and organizer for the Class of 1889. Many letters relate to reunion arrangements, and frequent correspondents include Lewis Welch, Gifford Pinchot, and George Parmly Day. The papers also contain many files relating to theater and the Yale Department of Drama. Some of these relate to the controversy surrounding the resignation of Monty Woolley as a coach of the Yale Dramatic Association.
Series II includes correspondence, notes, and drafts relating to Fisher's research on Thomas Collier, an eighteenth century printer in Litchfield, Connecticut, and his publication of Publications of Thomas Collier, Printer in the early 1930s. The files contain notes on the locations of almanacs printed by Collier, a manuscript of a biography of him, Fisher's correspondence with the Yale Printing Service, and letters of acknowledgement and congratulation.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Herbert Fisher was born in Cincinnati, Ohio on May 26, 1867. He received B.A. (1889) and LL.B. (1892) degrees from Yale University. Fisher practiced law in New Haven, Connecticut and New York City and served as junior counsel to Yale University and personal counsel to Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness and Edward S. Harkness. He was a fellow of the Yale Corporation (1920-1935) and chaired the Connecticut tercentenary commission (1934-1935). Fisher died in 1957.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Education, Higher; Litchfield (Conn.) -- History; Lawyers; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949; Baker, George Pierce, 1866-1935; Bannard, Otto Tremont, 1854-1929; Cheney, Howell; Collier, Thomas, 1761-1842; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Fisher, Samuel H. (Samuel Herbert), 1867-1957; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-1977; Lohmann, Carl A. (Carl Albert), 1887-; Oviatt, Edwin, 1874-1955; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Rogers, James Gamble, 1867-1947; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Welch, Lewis Sheldon, 1867-1940; Woolley, Monty, 1888-1963; AYA (Organization); Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1889; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Buildings; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Presidents; Yale University -- Students; Yale Corporation; Yale University. Dramatic Association
- YALE UNIVERSITY FILES, 1916-1954; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Alumni Advisory Board
    - General, 1922-1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alumni Association scholarships, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni Committee of Yale University, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3-11)
  - Alumni Committee of Yale University, 1919-1920, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 12-24)
  - Athletic-Association, 1926, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Building Committee
    General note
    See also: box 14, folders 185-187
    - General, 1917-1935 (Box 3, Folder 26-36)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1921-1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 37-39)
    - Day and Klauder, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Downey, John I., 1922 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Farnam, Thomas W., 1921-1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 42-44)
    - Minutes and papers, 1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Chapel matters, 1925-1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - Christian Association, 1925-1949, undated (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - Committee on Colleges, 1933-1934, undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Committee on Educational Policy, 1925-1926, undated
    See: box 8, folders 95-96 box 20, folders 261-266
  - Committee on Honorary Degrees, 1925-1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
  - Committee on Taxes
    - General, 1933-1935 (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
    - Taxation and New Haven, 1917-1927 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Yale University, 1930, 1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 56-59)
  - Corporation
    See also: box 20, folders 261-270
    - Baker, George Pierce, 1929-1933 (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Bannard, Otto T., 1920-1926 (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Buckner, Mortimer N., 1921-1928 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Cheney, Howell, 1921-1927 (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1916-1929 (Box 5, Folder 64-66)
    - Farnam, Thomas W., 1920-1925 (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Finance Committee, 1921-1930 (Box 6, Folder 68-70)
    - Gallery of Fine Arts, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Hutchins, Robert M., 1923-1927 (Box 6, Folder 72-73)
      See also: box 4, folders 51-52
    - Jones, Frederick S., 1921-1925 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Lohmann, Carl A., 1927-1930 (Box 6, Folder 75-76)
      See also: box 11, folders 151-160
    - A-O, 1920-1930 (Box 25, Folder 1-4)
    - P - Z, 1920-1935 (Box 6, Folder 77-79)
    - Revision of bylaws, 1919, 1929-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 80-81)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1920-1922 (Box 7, Folder 82-83)
    - Successors to the Original Trustees, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Welch, Lewis Sheldon, 1920-1925 (Box 7, Folder 85-86)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1921-1927 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Day, George Parmly, 1921-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 88-89)
    See also: box 5, folder 64-66 box 8, folder 103-104 box 15, folder 197 box 15, folder 199-219
  - Department of Drama, 1931-1934 (Box 7, Folder 90)
    See also: box 5, folder 60 box 14, folders 192-193
  - Department of Education, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Dramatic Association, 1917-1930 (Box 7, Folder 92-94)
    See also: box 14, folders 194-196
  - Educational policy, 1930-1935 (Box 8, Folder 95-97)
    See also: box 20, folders 261-266
  - Endowment Fund
    - General, 1920-1928 (Box 8, Folder 98-99)
    - Angell, James Rowland, 1921-1927 (Box 8, Folder 100)
    - Bannard, Otto T., 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 101)
    - Buckner, Mortimer N., 1925-1927 (Box 8, Folder 102)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1920-1930 (Box 8, Folder 103-104)
    - Gifts and bequests: reports of treasurer, 1922-1930 (Box 8, Folder 105)
    - Papers, 1923-1925 (Box 8, Folder 106)
    - Use of income, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 107)
    - Webb, Estate of Gertie E. Gorman, 1923-1924 (Box 8, Folder 108)
    - Woodruff house, 1927-1929 (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Harkness Recitation Hall, 1924-1926 (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Institute of Human Behavior, 1928, undated (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Institute of International Studies, 1944-1945, undated (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - Memorial concerts, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Nathan Hale Inn and Tapping Reeve Inn, 1927-1929 (Box 9, Folder 114-115)
  - Pierson, George, 1942-1953 (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - President, 1921-1948 (Box 9, Folder 117-130)
  - Provost, 1928-1946, undated (Box 10, Folder 131-137)
  - Publishing Association
    - Watrous, Hewitt, Sheldon and Gumbart, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - Yale Alumni Weekly, 1917-1923 (Box 10, Folder 139-141)
    - Yale Rep, 1918-1935 (Box 10, Folder 142)
  - Quadrangle plan, 1930-1931 (Box 10, Folder 143)
  - School of Forestry, 1921-1929, undated (Box 11, Folder 144-145)
  - School of Medicine, 1918-1931 (Box 11, Folder 146-149)
  - School of Music, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 150)
  - Secretary's office, 1928-1953, undated (Box 11, Folder 151-160)
    See also: box 6, folder 67 box 6, folders 72-73 box 6, folders 75-76 box 7, folders 82-83
  - Special Committee on the Presidency, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 161-172)
  - Special Committee on the Presidency, 1920-1921, undated (Box 13, Folder 173-184)
  - Sperry Engineering Company: controversy, 1921-1924 (Box 14, Folder 185-187)
  - Sterling Memorial Library, 1917-1954 (Box 14, Folder 188-191)
  - Yale Theatre
    - Personal, 1927-1930 (Box 14, Folder 192-193)
    - Woolley matter
      - General, 1927-1928 (Box 14, Folder 194)
      - Papers, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 195)
      - Yale Daily, 1927 (Box 14, Folder 196)
        See also: box 19, folders 252-254
  - Treasurer's office, 1935-1946, undated (Box 15, Folder 197)
    See also: box 5, folders 64-66 box 7, folders 88-89
  - Trumbull College, 1934-1942, undated (Box 15, Folder 198)
  - Yale Alumni University Fund Association: Class of 1889, 1937-1943 (Box 15, Folder 199-210)
  - Yale Alumni University Fund Association: Class of 1889, 1943-1948 (Box 16, Folder 211-219)
  - Yale Club of New York, 1937-1948, undated (Box 17, Folder 220-221)
  - Yale College Class of 1889
    - General, 1934-1947 (Box 17, Folder 222-231)
    - Banks, John W., 1936-1948 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Corbin, William H., 1942-1945 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Donnelly, Thomas E., 1934-1948 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Ensign, Joseph R., 1936-1940 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Pinchot, Gifford, 1936-1945 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Reed, Harry Lathrop, 1934-1948 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Vernon, Howard W., 1936-1942 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Welch, Lewis S., 1936-1939 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Fiftieth reunion, 1938-1939, undated (Box 18, Folder 232-237)
    - Fifty-fifth reunion, 1943-1944, undated (Box 18, Folder 238-243)
    - Fifty-sixth reunion, 1945 (Box 18, Folder 244)
    - Fifty-seventh reunion, 1946, undated (Box 19, Folder 245-246)
    - Fifty-eighth reunion, 1947 (Box 19, Folder 247)
    - Fifty-ninth reunion, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 248)
    - Sixtieth reunion, 1948-1949 (Box 19, Folder 249-251)
  - Yale Daily: Woolley matter, 1927 (Box 19, Folder 252-254)
  - Yale-in-China, 1920-1951 (Box 19, Folder 255)
  - Yale Law School, 1923-1948, undated (Box 20, Folder 256-260)
  - Yale Theatre
    See: box 14, folders 192-196
  - Yale University: general, 1919-1930, undated (Box 20, Folder 261-268)
  - Yale University: general, 1931-1953, undated (Box 21, Folder 269-278)
  - Yale Re, 1920-1929 (Box 21, Folder 279)
    See also: box 10, folder 142
- THOMAS COLLIER FILES, 1930-1948; Series II
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic or record type.
  - Almanacs, 1932, undated (Box 22, Folder 280-281)
  - Bibliography, 1932-1933, undated (Box 22, Folder 282-285)
  - Biography: manuscript, 1932 (Box 22, Folder 286-293)
  - Collier and Monitor, undated (Box 23, Folder 294)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1948, undated (Box 23, Folder 295-297)
  - Imprints
    - General, 1931-1933, undated (Box 23, Folder 298-303)
    - Authors, undated (Box 23, Folder 304)
    - Miscellanea, 1932 (Box 23, Folder 305-307)
  - Later years, undated (Box 24, Folder 308)
  - Notes, undated (Box 24, Folder 309-312)
  - "Politics of that day,", 1930 (Box 24, Folder 313)
  - Publications of Thomas Collier, Printer
    - Correspondence, 1933-1945, undated (Box 24, Folder 314-317)
    - Mailing lists, 1933 (Box 24, Folder 318)